<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <title>Melati - Java SQL Website Development Engine</title>
  </head>
  <properties>
    <author email="timp@paneris.org">Tim Pizey</author>
  </properties>

  <body>


    <!--
    <p align="center">
     <font size="-1"><i>
    This page last updated: $Date$ $Author$
     </i></font>
    </p>
    -->

    <!-- menu -->

    <section name=" Database Design ">
      <p>
        POEM makes some assumptions about database design best practice.
      </p>
      <subsection name=" Table and Field Naming ">
        <p>
          Ideally database table names are all lowercase, the java class name
          will be all lowercase with first letter capitalised.
        </p>
        <p>
          Whatever case you use in the DSD will be respected and reflected in the
          java class names, method names and database table names created.
        </p>
        <p>
          Names cannot start with a number.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name=" Keys ">
        <p>
          All tables are expected to have a unique field called<tt>id</tt>, it is this field
          that is used when this record is referred to in another record.
        </p>
        <p>
          Keys are dataless, unchanging, unique and unambiguous (DU<sup>3</sup>)
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name=" Indexing ">
        <p>
          All fields designated as searchable have an index created on them if they do not already have one.
          Melati assumes that the dbms will plan queries effectively using whatever keys it has available.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name=" The database application balance ">
      <p>
        The balance of responsibility between an application and its datastore is a key consideration
        in the architecture of a system.
      </p>
      <p>
        POEM is designed to enable rapid prototyping and to be database agnostic. This means that
        POEM attempts to make as little use as possible of the underlying database management system (DBMS).
        The DBMS syntax required is split out into the
        <tt>dbms</tt>
        package where each dbms idiosyncrasy
        is made explicit.
        This makes switching applications from one dbms to another trivial and often effortless.
      </p>
      <p>
        The project however may require more extensive use of the underlying DBMS, perhaps the
        care and maintenance of the database is to be handed over to a dedicated DBA or there may be a
        a desire to use a schema graphing tools (such as
        <a href="http://schemaspy.sourceforge.net" title="Cool schema graphing tool">Schema Spy</a>).
        To enable this there is an optional property on a Melati
        <tt>LogicalDatabase</tt>
        to add constraints.
        When set primary key constraints, foreign key constraints and referential integrity constraints
        are added to the database.
      </p>
      <p>
        Constraints are added after the database has been initialised, to avoid the problem of
        referring to a table in a foreign key before it has been created.
      </p>
      <p>
        Note that there may be a downside to adding constraints. It may mean that you need to manually
        delete these constraints before being able to alter your table structure.
      </p>
      <subsection name=" Primary Key Constraints ">
        <p>
          POEM only ensures that primary keys are indexed and unique and creates such an index if it is missing.
        </p>
        <p>
          When the
          <tt>AddConstraints</tt>
          property is set then Primary Key constraints are added to
          the Table Row Id (TROID) column of all tables.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name=" Foreign Key Constraints ">
        <p>
          POEM does not use the DBMS' Foreign Keys, as it maintains its own metadata in the
          <tt>ColumnInfo</tt>
          table, but for schema export or reporting this metadata needs to be
          known by the DBMS.
        </p>
        <p>
          The
          <tt>AddConstraints</tt>
          property allows the setting of these constraints.
        </p>
        <p>
          Foreign Keys should not have any impact upon a Melati system, though there is a chance of
          increased or decreased performance depending upon your DBMS.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name=" Referential Integrity Constraints ">
        <p>
          POEM has its own mechanism for ensuring referential integrity.
          The standard referential integrity policies correspond to those found in most modern DBMS.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>
              POEM
            </th>
            <th>SQL</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>prevent</td>
            <td>RESTRICT</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>delete</td>
            <td>CASCADE</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>clear</td>
            <td>SET NULL</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Of course if you have written your own POEM
          <tt>IntegrityFix</tt>
          fix then
          this will not be communicated to the DBMS.
        </p>
        <p>
          Note that POEM does not have an equivalent of
          <tt>ON UPDATE</tt>
          as POEM keys are
          intended to be unchanging.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>












